so this is suited on the seven awakening
factors
it begins when ebiku is accomplished in
virtue composure understanding
and who has full knowledge and
free freedom
the sight of them is
very helpful to hear them to approach
them to respect them to recollect them
or to take up the training and follow
them that is also very helpful
and why is that
because after hearing the teaching of
such renunciants a renunciant will live
renunciants a renunciant will live
withdrawn in both body and mind
[Music] and then it continues
and then it continues
as they
recollect and think about that teaching
at such a time
a renunciant has obtained or activated
the awakening factor of mindfulness they
develop it and perfect it
so just by thinking about that teaching
you're mindful
in the correct sense of that word
you are collected
you're established in the right context
otherwise you won't be able to think
about the particulars of the teaching
so now if i
so i meet some you meet someone who's a
who's has understood the dharma and then you
has understood the dharma and then you
reflect on that teaching
i have the awakening factor of
mindfulness well because i'm thinking about the
well because i'm thinking about the
teaching well if you have if you are
thinking about the actual teaching in
other words if you understood them
correctly then yes
not like so thinking about the dharma
is not an enlightened enlightenment
factor
like thinking about the information you
have on dhamma that's not
the same as understanding the meaning
the chord of the dharma
and so if you understood the dharma
so if you understood the dharma
then when you think about it the
enlightenment factors will be brought to
fulfillment but if you haven't understood the dharma
but if you haven't understood the dharma
for yourself
you can think about the dhamma all you
want about it it won't be it won't be on the
about it it won't be it won't be on the
level of enlightenment factors because
it's not on the level of insight
so but before we get into discussion
what are the enlightenment factors
uh mindfulness
and then uh
dhammavi china investigation into
dumbest effort effort
joy calm
calm
composure and economicity economics
so that's
yeah so that's the first things
basically it's the see
[Music] and that's kind of the problem with most
and that's kind of the problem with most
of the
things you read in the suttas it's that
it's been so long ago
since they were taught
they were remembered and the only way to
remember those things was through these
like linear lists like one two three
four five six seven
or four of this or eight of them or 12
of this
and people then be and that's just mere
information that's just just pure
inflammation or there's several lifetime
factors to somebody who doesn't have a
clue somebody who's enlightened
he doesn't even need to he doesn't he
might not even know about enlightenment
factors in that order in that list in
that particular way the buddha taught on
some occasion so
so
that's that's like the important thing
to to realize uh if you want to
contemplate the enlightenment factors or
if you like nobody for path it's exactly
the same thing it's not one two three
four five six seven eight
as many so to say no it's like the right
view and right mindfulness and then
whether it's the right effort through
that it's right because of the right
view and the right mindfulness whether
it is the right speech through that it's
right because of right view and right
mindfulness so it's like this right view
comes first
and then
mindfulness through that is right and
the direction of your ref is right or
your livelihood is right but it's not
like i develop the right view then i go
for the second step it's not a
step-by-step arrangement and neither is
several item effectors which is exactly
he goes and hears the wise people he
understands what they teach so he actually
what they teach so he actually
understands
he develops he he becomes a certified he
develops the right view
now on the basis of that correct
view standpoint
when he thinks about the dharma when he
is mindful those enlightenment factors
develop but not by not having the right view and
but not by not having the right view and
thinking about the list of enlightenment
factors yeah if i if i
yeah if i if i
do these things these seven things
they will be
if i do step by step these these seven
steps it will culminate in in complete uh
it will culminate in in complete uh
enlightenment but i have no clue
what that enlightenment is i have no
right view in regard to the you know
escape from suffering and where the
practice is
so i'll just basically use the
information that i have on the level of
lists and collections and steps and methods
and collections and steps and methods
and instructions and i'll adhere to it
which like hopefully it will kind of
bring me the result but
as the opening bid you read it already
says no first you need to understand
then these factors will come to
fulfillment and development so without
understanding without a right view there
are no seven enlightenment factors in
you doesn't matter how much you think
about him
if on the other hand you don't think
about him as this
methodical list by list step list
step-by-step instructions
but actually try to understand the
nature what is correct mindfulness what
is the correct investigations of
phenomena what is the correct effort
what is um samadhi somalia comes
just before equanimity
yet here i am believing i can practice
samad even without a right view they
will somehow result in enlightenment but
as an enlightenment factor is just one
towards just just before like
combination of arahantship the properly
fulfilled tamari
and there are all these things that i
need to develop beforehand
all of that you can infer from reading
the sutta so ah have i developed all
these things beforehand have i truly
developed the right view
that then makes me correctly mindful
that that makes me
correctly thinking about the dhammas
that then brings the joy and calm and so
on
or am i just fabricating joy or hoping
for a calm as a kind of magical result
of my method of my technique so that i
don't have to drill the work and and go
through the painful process of trying to
gain the understanding
yeah so these factors are
factors of an awakened person that he's
developed an awakened person is
developing these facts yeah it's these
are factors uh again like many other
things mentioned in the sutures
are the factors for somebody who has the
right view
so somebody who knows what
uh how to get to the end result how to
how to fully achieve enlightenment but
hasn't done it yet
so these factors are the factors that he
should dwell on and contemplate and uh
and they will come to fulfillment if he
just follows the direction of his own
right view
so the usefulness of why the buddha
listed seven these seven factors is for
those who have kind of attained to the
right view but haven't completed the
work so it's a good reminder to them oh look
so it's a good reminder to them oh look
it's only these things these are seven
aspects of the same thing that you
already have that you already understood
that already pre freed you partially
so dwell on these seven aspects and they
will in return basically
bring other aspects to fulfillment
i remember first coming across it and
trying to do these things
and you're sitting there meditating
whatever watching watching the breath
and then you you try and look for those
those things i'm making an effort yeah i
am mindful yeah am i yeah well i'm
investigating yeah i feel quite calm
yeah i'm happy
and you know oh
composed somebody looks very close to
nibana where is it where is it yeah just
keep it going and then
yeah yeah
no that is that is sort of the
but like a normal especially you know due to
like a normal especially you know due to
the whole like epidemic stuff and
commentarial where the whole time was
presented is just basic collection of
lists and and myriad of like information
and this and and parallels and and so on
but none of that is actually the dharma
dharma begins with the understanding of
the principle
if you don't understand the principle of
freedom from suffering like the four
noble truth is just one principle with
four aspects if you fully understand it
you understood the four facets of one
inside uh without that there is no dhamma even
uh without that there is no dhamma even
if you know all of the sutures by heart
and and all of the information you've
collected
and that's something that people don't
necessarily know because again you know
you're presented with so much stuff
today um and so many different takes so then
um and so many different takes so then
you come to you you come and read
various things and then you immediately
naturally sort of try to make sense out
of it but you're not aware that you're
actually reading into it you're not
you're not
you're not transparent enough you don't
have the right basis you don't have the
gradual training developed so when you
come across this information you're kind
of taking it as information that's being
misunderstood for understanding and most
people's understanding is that just a
collection of information
and when they sort of have one
information and they contrast another
piece of information another piece of
information and develop like a greater
information and so on it's it's a form
of understanding but it's not a form of
understanding that pertains on that
individual personal level internally to
be known by the wise as the reader says
so basically the one that pertains to
freedom from suffering from which amount
for which no amount of information will
will suffice to free you only that
insight into foreign novel truths would
so that's the important uh thing to
realize is right so if you don't have
the right view
that must be your your soul kind of goal
is to develop right view
uh insight into freedom from suffering
to know for yourself the origin
the uh
the suffering the origin the cessation
and the path that leads to cessation of
suffering so when that's understood then
within that understanding you have the
right mindfulness you have the noble
eiffel path you have the seven
enlightenment factors you have the four
right striving whichever aspect you it's
within that
and you will know that ah through
developing this one insight and state of
mind that i have that i kind of work for
i am developing this and now if you want
to develop it more
astutely more precisely more efficiently
you then
study further the information about the
seven enlightened factors so that you
can apply it correctly within that basis
that you have but if you don't have the
basis it's just a collection of
information and dangerous in a way because very
and dangerous in a way because very
dangerous because information is just
too easy to be
uh
misconceived confused mistaken for
understanding so like when you have so much
so like when you have so much
information or like
again i don't want to sound out too much
like too much thinking or something
or too much information is bad
it's dangerous because of the wrong
attitude underneath which means
whether you have the information or not
the wrong attitude is really what keeps
you ignorant
so don't don't think now on the like
that if you are getting i must not get
all this information because it's
dangerous no your ignorance is dangerous
no your ignorance is dangerous
so you have to always keep perspective
in regard to that oh i am ignorant and
i'm collecting information now i'm
learning about the suitors i'm not
taking anything for granted i'm taking
everything with a pinch of salt
until i know for myself the way out of
suffering that's the only criteria
nothing shorter than sorta party should
be a criteria of success
but if you don't have that authentic
attitude then whether you have a little
bit of information a lot of information
well makes no difference because you're
already obscured by yourself by by being
obscured by yourself by by being
ignorant by not having that right
attitude that that pertains to freedom from
that that pertains to freedom from
suffering as the only measure of
understanding not the satisfaction of you know making
not the satisfaction of you know making
the sense out of information and so on
so i'm reluctant to even talk about
didn't even speak about this to provide
all the information
yeah [Music]
[Music]
i'll just continue as the first one as
they recollect and think about that
teaching at such a time a renunciant
at such a time a renunciant
with the right view has obtained the
awakening factor of mindfulness
they develop it and perfect it
and when they investigate and explore
and enquire into teaching wisdom at such
a time they have the awakening factor of
damage right so see another another um
aspect of that see that all the
alignment factors are kind of peripheral
secondary when he investigates
when he investigates
the mindfulness gets developed
when he thinks and ponders about that
teaching he understood dhammavici it
gets developed
not he thinks about dhammavich and
that's how tamariche gets developed
no he thinks about the dhamma ponders
and dhamma or fortifies his
understanding of dhamma that effort is
the development of dhammavicher
secondarily
he doesn't think
being developed no it clearly says that
when he does this mindfulness get
developed while he's doing this dharma
victory has developed
okay so as as he investigates completes
a dhamma with understanding in this way
his effort is uh activated
and is unshaken at such a time
renunciant has activated the awakening
factor indirectly again striving yeah while
indirectly again striving yeah while
he's making the effort to to clarify
what he understood to fortified
to sustain to protect that context
everything we talk about all that that
he invests in that brings the
the enlightenment factor of of effort to
fulfillment not oh i shall fulfill this effort
not oh i shall fulfill this effort
towards enlightenment
the phenomenon of striving is being
developed yeah
so indirectly that's the point because
he's triumphed he's striving towards the
goal of freedom from suffering that he
understood but hasn't fully fortified
so yeah
the direction of the right view the
understanding that you get through the
right view the effort you're putting
into furthering that understanding is
the enlightenment factor of effort and
striving
and when they make when he makes such
effort joy arises and then he's attained that
joy arises and then he's attained that
uh
enlightenment fact of joy yeah
so joy arises on its own as a result as
a product
of
his as a byproduct yeah exactly not like
oh i should be joyful and i'll let me
bring this joy now because that's
another factor that the buddha talks
about no follow the direction of the
right view
don't fall from it don't neglect it
don't become negligent or complacent
joy will arise on account of the effort
that you invested in following their
direction
and then when that
mind is joyous the body and mind become
calm yeah unified and calm
so again that's not something he does
let me let me unify this now
let me fulfill that which understood let
me dwell further on the understanding of
the four noble truths let me fortify
them and that will count down your mind
and you will that that you will
establish somebody like that that's the
establishment
so it's not the oh let me directly
attend to this that will concentrate my
mind on account of my effort to
concentrate my mind
it's completely go in the direction of
that right view yeah go in the direction
the right understanding the right view
which is the right mindfulness the
correct investigation of phenomena and
so on
and that results in in
towards that direction being fully
committed directed composed
uh in in that one way
and that's that's one pointedness not
one pointness of your tip of your nose
or something
it's one pointedness of the direction
towards freedom from suffering composed
in that one direction
that's like one way only for the one who
practices rightly the satipatanas
so no right view
no enlightenment factors no right view
no samadhi no right view no freedom from
suffering no understanding no wisdom no
uh equanimity
so if you think you have somebody and
you think you have equanimity and you
think you have joy without a right view
knowing that you don't have the right
view take them uh with a pinch of salt
recognize that they might not be
the one the the correct samadhi and
correct economic because there is no
right view so it's not to say oh there
is no samadhi at all there's no form of
samadhi at all but it's important to
recognize that the wrong samadhi
mistaken to be the right samadhi cannot
magically become the right's money only
fully abandoning
that with the the samadhi of the wrong
kind that you have the equanimity and
peace of the wrong kind that you have
fully abandoning it in order to get the
right view through exposure of that
recognition to you know towards
suffering and so on that's how you can
get then the right samadhi
because sometimes people might think oh
well you know i know my somali is all
right but if i keep investing any effort
in in this wrong samadhi it would become
right no
right samadhi is the result
of right view and correctly directed
mind right samadhi is not the
right samadhi is not the
result of repairing the wrong samadhi
that's already the wrong view thinking
you can directly attend to your samadhi
as a form of concentration that would
then result in some liberation
see you don't concentrate your mind
there towards your own concentration and
develop your samadhi through focusing
and so on
you develop samadhi by following the the
right view the which which is sort of uh
guided by the right mindfulness and
correct investigation of the factors and
joy and calm and effort
and that becomes a unification of the
mind so
it's equally secondary the right smart
it's indirect it's it's basically
peripheral from where you are making
your effort towards understanding
freedom from suffering
it's it's this little section is found
in
my gymnica 117
these three states run and circle around
each other right view
right effort
all right these three states run and
circle around right view
right view
right effort and right mindfulness yeah so it's
so it's
always those three if you have the right
view means there is a degree of right effort
means there is a degree of right effort
and there certainly means there is a
degree of right mindfulness
if you have right mindfulness the right
view is there and right f is there
if you have right effort the right view
is brought back in the right mind is it
there so that's what i mean they're not linear
so that's what i mean they're not linear
and if you try to
understand them on the level of their
linear information you will fail because
they cannot be attended to directly
and be understood in their nature you
can attend information directly okay there
attend information directly okay there
is one two three four five six seven
but what does that information pertain
to well pertain to pertains to
understanding freedom from suffering
what's suffering well suffering that i'm
liable here and now
so instead of me making the effort to
make to sort of draw connections and
parallels that nobody else thought of
and somehow get a magical insight on
account of it between these seven
factors let me dwell
let me dwell
dwell on the level of my liability to
suffering endure it
not try to get rid of it to manage it
which is why you always try to
jump and pounce on the information
hoping it will bring you freedom because
you want to get rid of the liability
that is painful
so the efforts to understand the dharma
if they're directed towards basically
uh manipulating and sort of uh
drawing parallels between information
that you collected
about the dhamma it's just going to
become another form of management of
your liability to suffering not the
uprooting of it
so yes you need the information you need
to be told what to do
but if you if you if you refuse to allow
yourself basically to come back onto the
level that it matters but that applies
you're just gonna stay on the level of
playing with information for the rest of
your life
because you refuse to give the attitude
of trying to manage your liability to
suffering by understanding information
and that's psychotherapy
that's psychology that's any any kind of
worldly way of dealing with suffering
and pain
it's all on the level of management
so it's only relatively efficient
so if you if you learn the seven factors
you learn the four noble truth
you learn the gradual training
you have more information than you need
as we said before
uh
back in the buddhist day there were no
suta collections
all the information we have now on
account of the the you know
the nikayas
like monks did not have access to that
only ananda was remember remembered all
of it most of the monks didn't and
probably vast majority of them knew maybe one
vast majority of them knew maybe one
story with one instruction
and there was enough for enlightenment
why why because they did the work
so if you know the four noble truth you
know the gradual training most
importantly you know what comes first
virtue sense restraint guiding of the
sense those you have all the information
you need
now you have to start doing that which
that information tells you and that's
the catch people don't do it
even when they take on the virtue take
on the gradual training they kind of
still keep it on the level of performing
the instruction gain on the level of
information because they don't want to endure
because they don't want to endure
the dukkha on that right level
that that liability to suffering they
don't want to feel it without
immediately trying to manage it because
it's too unpleasant if you just
give up the management
and just stay under that pressure of
that unresolved liability to suffering on the
unresolved liability to suffering on the
most on the deepest existential
level but you have to basically
if the right view were to sort of
take the route and start to grow it can
only do on that basis that's what i said
if somebody well he teaches only two
things suffering and freedom from it
so if somebody correctly understands the
nature of dukkha there are only two
outcomes of that
either mental derangement or noble
search as in okay
this if they don't lose their mind on account
if they don't lose their mind on account
of the recognition of that correct pain
of liability to suffering
that existential dread if they don't
lose the mind on account of it then they
will have no other choice
have no other choice
but to try and correctly uproot it
and seek the correct information they
will then sort of you know be the basis
for them making the right effort and
enduring things on the right level
so it comes down to that and during
things on the right level if you endure
things on the level of that existential
duke without trying to manage it get rid
of it
uh distract yourself from it then
then
the whole basis for the right view and
everything else that comes from it is
being developed
so that's that fundamental difference
between information
information
and understanding of it it's two
opposite directions
so information gives you
something that needs to be understood
but only your effort to understand
can bring that understanding not more
information more information cannot
accidentally result in understanding
only your effort to understand
so yeah most of the monks didn't have 99
of the suitors that we have today
and in a way see that was good their
minds were less cluttered with so many
information and then with that natural
tendency to draw parallels between
information instead of understanding
each and every one individually on that
personal basis
so it's like when a person reads about
narupa and then reads about the five aggregates
and then reads about the five aggregates
and then tries to understand how nama
rupa relates to five aggregates
and drawing parallels between
develops the belief that oh see i
understood this now because look i found
the common ground the connection
and that's just a connection of further
information if you were truly authentic
the way i'm talking about if you endure
the suffering on the right level
namarupa or the five aggregates or the
sixth sense basis doesn't matter which
one needs to be understood within itself
on the personal basis so you need to
understand narupa
to the extent that it frees you from
suffering or at least offers the direction of
or at least offers the direction of
freedom from suffering or you need to
understand the five aggregates
to the to the extent that frees you from
suffering or salayatana to the extent
that frees you from suffering
not hmm nawarupa relates to the
pharmacists which is all on the basis of
all of that came much later when people
have all this information and
fell away
from that personal basis of recognition
of their own liability to suffer
so then it's just too easy to start
conflating information and connection
between information with like greater
understanding and then got even worse people started
and then got even worse people started
studying poly scholastically
and then learning the etymology of the
informational term
developed a belief that you understood
it
but if you truly understood vinyana for
example you'll be an argument because it would
you'll be an argument because it would
have said complete understanding of
vinyana means other hanship so
so
all of that doesn't matter how much
information you have
and how much
how dependent you became on that
information all of that can be cleaned
away like in one sweep of just
re-establishing yourself
if you're brave enough and strong enough
to endure it on the level of i am still
liable to sickness aging death anxiety
dread suffering
i know no escape from it internally
i am not able to not move when these
things present themselves which is why i
always try to avoid those things from
presenting themselves i always try to
cover up when they are present
with the possibility of their presence
i always try to ignore and distract
myself from it
so if you abandon these attitudes
and endure these things on the right
level even the little information you
even the little information you
collected will start slotting itself in
the right place
because now you've got the basis that's
why the two factors for the right view
it's yes correct information utterance
of another
and the only suman sikara
the peripheral attention base is
properly developed
without it there is no right view
even if you listen to the buddha himself
giving information